Well, sitting on my desk is a new Mac
mini that I set up just for the purpose
of running my team of AI agents using
Open Claw. I've got a developer, a
marketer, a project manager, a system
admin. They each have their own
personality. They've got a queue of
tasks tracked in this custom dashboard
that I built. And I'm chatting with them
in Slack just like I would with my real
team members, except they're agents
powered by Open Claw and various large
language models. What a time this is.
But you know, getting this up and
running was not a plug-and-play
situation. Over the past week and many
late nights, I had to figure out my
answers to question after question. Some
technical, some strategic. Like, should
I order a new Mac mini or can I run Open
Claw on a VPS? And what's this going to
cost me in API tokens? And can I use my
Claude Max plan? And what chat tool is
best for my agents? Telegram or WhatsApp
or Slack? Should I have it power one
agent or can I set up a team of agents?
And am I going to need a custom
dashboard for managing them?
And let's not forget about security.
What should my agents be able to access
and how should I think about safeguards?
And most importantly, what's my use case
here? What will I have my team of agents
actually do for me? So, today I'll share
where I've landed on all of those
questions and I'll show you my setup for
all of it. You know, to be honest, I
didn't see the appeal of Open Claw at
first. Back when it was called Claude
Bot and then Multibot and it was buzzing
around Twitter a couple weeks ago,
everyone was talking about having their
agent respond to their emails for them
or book flights or order takeouts. And I
don't want or need an AI agent in my
personal life and I don't even want it
to manage my calendar. But then I
started thinking about a real challenge
that I've been having in my business and
how setting up Open Claw could help me
solve it. You know, I run this YouTube
channel and Build It Methods Pro and my
courses and a weekly newsletter. And
thanks to things like Claude code, of
course, building things has never been
easier, but building is only half of
what I I
I develop training content, I manage a
publishing pipeline, and I oversee my
membership business. But lately, I've
been bottlenecked. There's so much more
that I want to create and deliver if
only I had the bandwidth. In my past
businesses, I solved this by hiring real
teams and building processes to help us
scale. And that worked, but the overhead
was real, too. So, when I gave OpenClaw
another look, I asked a different
question. Not do I want a personal
assistant, but what if this could fill
roles on my team?
And now I'm convinced that this
paradigm, autonomous agents with defined
roles running on their own machines, I
think this is here to stay. Now,
OpenClaw is just the first generation of
what I think will be much bigger. So, I
want to be figuring this out now, and
maybe this video can help you get
started, too. If you're new here, I'm
Brian Castle. I help builders stay ahead
of the curve with AI. And every Friday,
I send my Builder Briefing. That's a
free 5-minute read where I give you my
no-hype take on making this transition
to adopting AI. You can get yours by
going to buildermethods.com.
And if you're serious about leveling up,
check out Builder Methods Pro where you
can join our community and get training
for builders. All right, so what
actually is OpenClaw? It used to be
called ClaudeBot, and then MaltBot. And
how is this actually different from how
you might use Claude Code or any other
agent? The core of OpenClaw is what's
called the gateway. That's a process
running on a machine, which shouldn't be
your personal machine. But we'll talk
about security in a moment. The OpenClaw
gateway can run tools, it can use a
browser, it can execute bash scripts. Of
course, Claude Code can do a lot of
that, too. But what makes OpenClaw
different is that it's always on. It
maintains a persistent workspace with
memory and session logs. So, you can
chat with your agents through Telegram
or Slack and delegate tasks that they
can do on their own in the background.
So, that's a fundamentally different
paradigm from you personally managing
Claude Code sessions in your terminal.
OpenClaw is is to having teammates who
do their work on their own workstations.
The first question is, where should this
thing run? Now, I don't recommend you
run Open Claw on your daily driver
machine. You don't want to give it
unfettered access to your files and your
accounts. And even if you isolate it
with something like Docker, your machine
would need to be on and awake 24/7 for
your agents to work. So, Open Claw needs
its own dedicated machine. That could be
a cloud VPS starting in around five
bucks a month, or it could be a physical
machine. Doesn't have to be a Mac mini,
any kind of computer on your network.
Both are valid, and a lot of people are
doing well with the VPS setups. But, I
went ahead and I spent the 600 bucks on
a new Mac mini M4. And call me old
school, but I like to be able to screen
share into it, see the desktop, install
things, and manage it visually. And I
SSH in, too, when I just need to run a
quick command.
And if I end up using my agent team for
all the use cases that I have in mind,
I'll need more storage and bandwidth
than the cheap VPS tiers offer. So, the
cost would start to balance out anyway.
And hey, if none of this works out, I'll
throw that Mac mini up in my home music
studio. I'll use it up there. So, I've
got the dedicated machine, but that's
just the first layer. I need to think
carefully about what my agents can and
can't access. Now, this is where the
hiring metaphor really kicked in. If I'm
bringing someone onto my team, I
wouldn't give them access to my personal
laptop or let them loose on a browser
where I'm logged into everything. No, an
employee would get their own machine,
their own email, access to the files and
services that they need with the right
permissions, nothing more. So, that's
what I did. I set up a dedicated email
address for my agents. I created a
GitHub username that I can invite to
specific repos. I can grant and revoke
access to services just like I would
with any other team member. Now, files
were a bit trickier. I want easy two-way
syncing between my computer and the Open
Claw workspace on the Mac mini,
especially since I'm developing a a
brain system where all my business
activity gets logged into markdown files
that my agents can access and work with.
More on the brain maybe another time.
So, all my files live either in GitHub
repos or my main Dropbox account. But, I
don't want to just share my personal
Dropbox with Open Claw. That gives it
access to way too much. So, I had Open
Claw set up its own Dropbox account. And
so, the specific folders that I want to
share between my main Mac and the Open
Claw Mac mini, both Dropbox accounts
have access to those. And so, everything
else stays walled off. All right, let's
talk about costs. Because if you're not
careful, you can easily run up hundreds
or even thousands of dollars in token
costs just chatting with your agents and
running tasks. I blew past $200 in the
first two days of setting up my system.
Now, I already pay for a Claude Max plan
and I was hoping that I could just use
that. But, then I heard the stories of
accounts being shut down because this
type of usage might be against
Anthropic's terms of service.
And then, within a few days, he upgraded
to the $200 subscription.
Uh euros, because he's in Austria. And
he was in love with that thing. That for
me was like a very early product
validation. It's like, I built something
that
captures
people. And then, a few days later,
Anthropic blocked him because, based on
their rules, using the subscription is
problematic or whatever. So, there's
real ambiguity there and I genuinely
wish that there would be some official
word, one way or the other. Now, I
intend to play by the rules. So, here's
where I landed. My Claude Max plan stays
for my personal use with Claude and
Claude code on my devices when I'm
working. My Open Claw agents use API
tokens, completely separate. I'm running
those tokens through Open Router, which
centralizes all my API usage and makes
it easy to select from hundreds of
models and providers. More importantly,
it lets me carefully optimize which
agents use which models for which tasks.
You know, honestly, that optimization is
probably where I spent the most time
this past week. Just figuring out which
tasks need the power of Opus and which
can run on cheaper, faster models.
Still, running this team of agents is
not cheap. And if you've been building
with the frontier models, then you
already know this isn't a free ride. And
from a business standpoint, if you
compare the token costs to the cost of
hiring multiple team members to do the
work that can, maybe should, be
delegated to agents, the ROI math gets
pretty compelling. Now, to the question
of chatting with my agents. Open Claw
supports a wide range of chat tools. I
started with Telegram since that was the
easiest to get up and running. It worked
for a few days and I was even able to
set up separate Telegram bots for each
agent. I'll talk about my multi-agent
configuration in just a minute. But
after a few days on Telegram, I found
the interface just wasn't comfortable,
especially when agents would send me
markdown formatted content, which kind
of works, kind of doesn't. So, again,
I'm working with my agents like I tend
to work with teammates, and my teams
have always used Slack. So, I set up
Slack bots for each of my agents and
that was super easy. And Slack has great
markdown support and I really like how
we can use threaded replies. And that
makes it easy to manage multiple agents
with multiple requests and responses
flying around. Now, here's what made
Open Claw really click for me. Instead
of using it as a single agent, I set up
a multi-agent configuration so that I
can build an actual team of four agents.
Claw is my system admin, who I work with
when I'm tinkering with my Open Claw
system itself. Bernard is my developer.
Val works on marketing tasks. And Gumbo
is my general assistant. Each agent runs
as its own Slack bot with its own
conversations. And I experimented with
having them all in a group chat, which
kind of works, but has some quirks. So,
I assigned a default model to each
agent. Opus for Bernard, the developer,
and Claw, the system admin. That's where
reasoning power really matters. And then
Sonnet for Val, the marketer, and Gumbo,
the assistant. That's where speed and
efficiency make more sense.
But I often direct them to delegate
parts of their work to sub-agents for
tasks where I need to specify a more
expensive model or a cheaper model.
Now, I decided to have them all share
one workspace, which means they all
access the same memory and I can manage
configurations and agents MD directives
all in one place. Also, my brain folder
lives in this workspace and that's where
all of our work gets synced up. And if
you want to hear more about my
productivity system with my agents, let
me know in the comments and I'll make
another video all about that. Now, Open
Claw has an identity.md file and that's
typically used to define a single
agent's identity,
but I use it to define multiple
identities, one for each agent on my
team.
I even used Claude and Gemini to develop
unique personality traits and a visual
avatar for each agent. I wanted to have
fun with it, you know, my bots are
characters inspired by one of my
favorite bands, Gorillaz.
Now, I did run into some challenges with
Open Claw's built-in cron system for
scheduled tasks. It was hard to
associate those tasks with specific
agents on my team. And so, that ended up
being one of the main reasons I built my
own custom dashboard and task
dispatching system.
So, I quickly realized that managing my
agents via chat alone was not going to
cut it. I wanted to see all my scheduled
tasks in one place and be able to assign
them to specific agents. And I wanted to
track token usage so I know how much all
of this is costing me. You know, I just
wanted a central dashboard where I could
see the whole system at a glance.
So, naturally, I built one. Any excuse
to build something, right? I used Claude
code and my design OS process and I had
a working app in about a day. It's a
simple Rails app that connects to Open
Claw's gateway and gives me a clean
interface for managing everything.
Honestly, that HQ dashboard was just the
beginning. Now, I'm building another app
for editing and reading markdown files
in my brain system so that I can easily
manage what my agents have access to.
This is what I love about this moment
for builders. When a tool that I need
doesn't exist yet, I just build it in a
day.
And the most important question, and the
one that I keep hearing everywhere, is
what are you actually going to use your
agents for? So, I've identified a few
specific areas where my agents can fill
real gaps in my business. Let's start
with the content that I publish. Now, I
only put things out when I have
something to say, and that will never
change. But, the truth is so much
happens inside my projects and in my
conversations with other builders that
never makes it to a video or a social
post. So, I'm building systems now that
let my agents observe and capture more
of that work and help me share more of
it across my platforms.
Second is development. Now, I still love
to spend most of my time in Claude code
and cursor designing and architecting
products. That's not going to change.
But, I'm having Bernard, my developer
agent, pick up backlog issues and track
production errors and submit PRs during
times when I can't get my hands on those
things.
Third is the glue work. This is a
bottleneck that I feel every single day.
Every minute that I spend project
managing or copying and pasting or
scheduling content or documenting
things, that's time that I'm not
thinking, creating, or building. And
those tasks should be automated or
delegated. And that's exactly what my
general assistant, Gumbo, is for. And
the use case that has me most excited is
reporting. So, having my agents surface
trends and patterns and new ideas on a
regular basis, helping me see blind
spots that I wouldn't notice on my own.
That's the kind of insight that helps me
teach ideas that actually help builders
get ahead and helps me create tools that
solve real problems.
Now, I've already started assembling the
building blocks, the processes for my
agents to follow, the automations, the
custom tooling. And I'd love to report
back on a future video to show you how
all that's coming together. So, make
sure you subscribe to the channel. Now,
I want to be careful not to oversell
Open Claw. It's still very early, very
raw, and I spent more late nights than
I'd like to admit just getting things
configured. But, there's no denying the
breakthrough as a concept that Open Claw
has broken open here, at least in our
circles of AI-pilled builders. And I see
this as one of those things that's worth
our extra effort to be an early adopter
on because systems like this are only
going to become more commonplace as this
year and next year play out. And that
gets at something that I think is a
fundamental skill for us as builders in
2026. We have to be willing to explore
and tinker to figure out how new tools
can help us make real progress in our
business. That's the value that we bring
to the table, and it's one of the five
essential skills that I think we need to
master to go from being overwhelmed by
the speed of change to actually thriving
in this new environment. And I cover all
five in my video on going from an AI
skeptic to building an unfair advantage.
So, right after you hit subscribe on the
channel, I'll see you on that one next.
Let's keep building.